Today's דף כ"ד, Daf Kaf Dalet, but we start where a half
of דף daf behind, we start at the top of דף כ"ג
עמוד ב'. Daf Kaf Gimmel Amud Bet. It actually is גמרא Gemara
that reads pretty easily, so I'll ask people to try to keep
questions to a minimum, and I think we can catch up today.
So, we are talking about a fetus that have appearances as animals,
and as we were saying in the גמרא Gemara yesterday that made
it sound like maybe you wouldn't think it is an animal, but
at least it looks like an animal, and whether that's considered a
fetus or not for purposes of childbirth. I just wanted by the
way repeat that I made the question yesterday but just to be
clear about it, I was making a distinction which was not, or
difference which really wasn't a distinction about whether the fetus was ever
viable or whether it just, you know, not, you know, was it
theoretically viable or not. Anyway, the distinction doesn't exist. The משנה Mishnah
in בכורות Bechorot that we quoted at the end of yesterday is
very simple and basically says that something that constitutes a fetus but
it's not born alive, it's born dead, so then it is a,
doesn't affect the question of בכור Bechor for the double portion because
the double portion is only goes by if it's the first child
or not the first child who is a living child. So if
it's a miscarriage, even if it would have been totally viable but
it was miscarried, you know, and it was born dead, not born
alive, then the, like a stillbirth or whatever, anyway, then the next
child would still be the firstborn for the double portion. But when
it comes to the issue of what's the firstborn for פדיון הבן,
Pidyon HaBen, then the תורה Torah more emphasizes, or says פטר רחם,
Peter Rechem, the one that sort of breaches the womb. So there
really it's anything that הלכתית Halachically constitutes a birth, even if it's
a miscarriage, if it הלכתית Halachically constitutes a birth, then the next
child is not the פטר רחם. Peter Rechem. And there the standard
of what constitutes a birth is pretty much the same as the
standard that we have for us about whether the mother is considered
a יולדת Yoledet for the laws of טומאה וטהרה, Tumah VeTaharah, whether
she's considered to have been in childbirth and therefore the debates about
well, what if the fetus looks like this animal, that's the same
debate about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים. Chachamim. But the
key difference there is that even if the child is born dead,
even a stillbirth, even a miscarriage, the mother would still be טמאה
Temeiah and the second child would not be פטר רחם. Peter Rechem.
So which by the way you should just be aware, mean that
there are, I think I mean we mentioned בכורות, Bechorot, but I
should just say, you know again, that actually the numbers of פדיון
הבןs Pidyon HaBen are pretty rare. I mean I know how many
people, how many פדיון הבןs Pidyon HaBen people have been to in
their lives. Right. כהנים Kohanim a little bit more if they're asked
actually to be the one that receives the money. But first of
all you have all the cases where a girl is born first.
You have all the cases where it was a miscarriage prior. Then
you have all the cases where the mother or the father is
a כהן Kohen or בת כהן, Bat Kohen, mother or father's a
לוי Levi or בת לוי. Bat Levi.
So then you have old siblings.
That's right. No, you mean, oh second, yeah, really old siblings, yeah,
I know what you said anyway. So, but just in my house
I think I told you this. So my wife's sister was married
to, is married to a כהן, Kohen, so their first child was
born, no פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen.
Her other sister is married to a לוי, Levi, their first child
was born, no פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. Then we were going to
have the next child in the family and our first, and we
knew it was a boy, so I figured, oh great, we'll finally
have a פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. So, very insightfully, no פדיון הבן.
Pidyon HaBen. So anyway,
but פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen even if it is a, what do
you call it, even if it's a miscarriage, and the only question
is is the fetus considered a fetus, and that is our issue
about what it looks like. So now we continue, it's about eight
lines from the top, a little א Aleph in brackets, middle of
the line. בעי רב אדא בר אהבה מאביי. Ba'ei Rav Adda Bar
Ahava MiAbaye. רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda Bar Ahava asked אביי.
Abaye. רבי מאיר דאמר בהמה במעי אמו, Rabbi Meir De'amar Behema Beme'ei
Imo, again the name the word בהמה, Behema, not looks like a
בהמה, Behema, it might be a shorthand, maybe not. I'll translate it
in the more sort of a softer way. According to רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that says a fetus that looks like an animal that's
in the mother's womb, ולד מעליא הוא, Velad Ma'alya Hu, and is
considered to be a real fetus for laws of childbirth, and here
you see why down like the גמרא's Gemara not just dealing with
appearances, well I don't know, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
בהמה? Behema? I know, I know. Anyway, אדם במעי בהמה מאי? Adam
Beme'ei Behema Mai? So let's say you have again, I'll translate literally,
a human in a, in the womb of a cow, what is
the הלכה Halacha be? So the גמרא Gemara says,
wait, what was the question?
Yeah, you're talking, you don't hear. So anyway,
למאי נפקא מינה? Lemai Nafka Mina? What difference does it make? Now
if the גמרא Gemara really thought that this was a human, you'd
say, what do you mean what difference does it make? Is it
חייב במצוות? Chayav BeMitzvot? Is it murder if you would kill it?
Like a million different things, are you considering it human or not
human? But the גמרא Gemara really asks it in a very narrow
question. Here's the גמרא's Gemara question: לאשתרויי באכילה. Le'ishtaru'ei Ba'achilah. Is it
considered to be a cow, you know, a calf, and you can
eat it, or is it considered to be some weird thing and
it's not considered to be a calf and it's therefore you can't
eat it. Anything that like maybe it's not—whatever it is, it's not
a cow. It's not a כשר kosher animal or whatever it is,
and therefore you can't eat it. Now again, notice that it did
not say that we would really consider it to be a human,
which is analogous to תוספות Tosafos aside, the גמרא's Gemara never really
suggested before that the fetus that looks like a בהמה behemah in
a human's womb is considered to be a בהמה. behemah. תוספות Tosafos
says it would be חייב chayav for bestiality, but the גמרא Gemara
doesn't say that. So which is why, I, you know, it seems
clear that the גמרא Gemara understands in the case of the human,
it's biologically human, and the case of the בהמה, behemah, it's biologically
בהמה, behemah, but it looks like this other thing. How far does
that change what its הלכתי halakhic status is?
כוסא דחזירתא, kosa de-chazirasa, right? Yeah. So the גמרא Gemara says
yes.
Did Rabbis understand that it's not actually possible?
So that I don't know. I don't know. Right. I don't know.
And that's why I don't know whether the language of בהמה בני
אדם behemah benei adam or אדם בני בהמה adam benei behemah means
looks like, or means that they really thought it was. But again,
the fact that it never is really suggesting that this could have
human status indicates that, you know, their understanding of it.
No, but also in the case of.
Right. Right. I don't know. I don't know. Yeah, I don't know.
I don't know. I don't know. So the גמרא Gemara says, ותפשוטה
v'tipshotei מהא דרבי יוחנן, mei-ha de-Rabbi Yochanan,
learn it out from what Rabbi Yochanan says. דאמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar
Rabbi Yochanan, השוחט את הבהמה ומצא בה דמות יונה, ha-shocheit es ha-behemah
u-matza bah demus yonah,
similar to what Mike was saying, אסורה באכילה. asura ba-achilah.
That if somebody slaughters a בהמה behemah and finds in it a
fetus—now notice again, דמות, demus, which is appearance. So the גמרא's Gemara
easy shift between describing it as the thing or looking like the
thing. So you find a fetus that looks like a dove, it
is forbidden because it's not a בהמה, behemah, and it's a, you
know, and therefore it didn't have a כשר kosher שחיטה shechitah or
whatever it is. It's not a dove, don't they שחט shecht it
now? But whatever it is, it's not part of a בהמה behemah
and therefore you can't eat it. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי
השתא, hachi hasha, what type of a comparison is that? התם לא
פרסות איכא ולא פרסה איכא. hasam lo parsos ika v'lo parsah ika.
There, it does not have split hooves or really even one hoof,
one foot.
הכא היא דפרסות ליכא ופרסה מיהא איכא, hacha hi d'parsos leka u-parsah
mi-ha ika, it does have one hoof, because the תורה Torah says,
you know, when it speaks about a בהמה, behemah, מפרסת פרסה, mafreses
parsah, that is split hooves, but it uses the word פרסה. parsah.
So therefore to understand that if something is in it that is
in none of the descriptors of a בהמה, behemah, not in the
פרסות parsos and not even in the פרסה, parsah, clearly it is
not judged as part of the בהמה behemah and cannot be eaten.
And that's something that looks like a bird. But something here that
looks like a human, you know, humans have feet, it doesn't have
split hooves but has feet, so to some degree it fits some
of the descriptors in the פסוק pasuk of פרסה, parsah, and therefore
maybe it's enough considered to be part of a בהמה behemah that
it can be eaten. But again notice, first of all, and this
is why I'm inclined to read the גמרא Gemara in I don't
think what's an apologetic way but a more understandable way, that this
easy shift between saying אדם adam and saying דמות, demus, you know,
דמות יונה, demus yonah, אדם, adam, what it looks like, I don't
think it literally believed that it was a human. And the other
proof is that if it really said it was a human, there
are huge נפקא מינות, nafka minas, not just can you eat it?
I mean, is it cannibalism? Come on. So I really think that
the גמרא Gemara understands that this is a בהמה, behemah, or in
the other case, by what's in the mother's fetus, that it's a
human. But the question is, how does its appearance, to what degree
does it change its הלכתי halakhic status? And here the question would
be, does it take it out of the category of בהמה behemah
that it can no longer be eaten? By the human, does it
take it out of the category of human that the mother is
not a יולדת, yoledes, and so on? That is the way I
am reading these questions.
I expected the גמרא Gemara to say the opposite, that a hoof,
it's not split, that that would be.
Oh, that could be. Not a foot. Yeah, I hear. That could
be, you mean in why consider it to be an animal, why
not just consider it to be like a piece of the inside,
of the inside of the בהמה? behemah? Yeah, that could be. Okay,
but it didn't do that. וחכמים אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, and the חכמים
Chachamim
say—now we go on. So the משנה Mishnah continued to say that
the חכמים Chachamim say anything that does not have צורת אדם, tsuras
adam, the appearance of a human, is not considered a fetus for
childbirth. So אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר רב, amar Rabbi Yirmiyah
bar Abba amar Rav, הכל מודים, hakol modim, everybody agrees, חכמים Chachamim
and רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, גופו טליא, gufo talyash,
if the body looks like a, like a ram, ופניו אדם, u-panav
adam, and the face is an אדם. adam. Now notice again, it
goes back to this point, it does not say the body looks
like a ram, the face looks like a human. It says the
body is a ram and the face is a human. So again,
I think that when it says is, that could just be shorthand
for looks like. Okay, so here clearly, we're not saying the whole
thing, we're describing what different body parts look like.
But from a human, from a human mother.
Right. Yes. Yes, yes, we're back to human mother. Yeah, we're back
to the משנה, Mishnah, back to human mother. Okay, so if the
body is that of a ram and the face is that of
a human, so אדם, adam, so then it has, everybody agrees what
it would be considered like a full human fetus and the mother
would be טמאה לידה. temei'ah leidah. So even when the Rabbis say
that it has to have צורת אדם, tsuras adam, this goes again
to the importance of the face, as long as the face looks
human, that is enough to give the fetus a status of human.
גופו אדם ופניו טליא, gufo adam u-panav talyash, what if it's the
opposite, the body looks human but the face looks like a ram,
interesting that they picked ram for whatever reason. ולא כלום, v'lo klum,
everybody agrees that that has no status of a human fetus, even
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Wait, what do you mean? רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir just got through saying that even if the whole thing looks
like an animal. So תוספות Tosafos says, you know, and I think
רש"י Rashi also applies or whatever, that there's a difference between if
it's this weird... hybrid than if it completely looks like something else.
Again, it's not exactly clear to me why that should be obvious.
I mean, if we're all agreeing that biologically it's human and you
want to say, but is it enough in terms of the appearance
to give it that status, then you would say that any part
that looks is better than nothing that looks like it. So why
if the whole thing looks like an animal, it should be more
status of a fetus than if it's a split? But I guess
split is just seen here, the way the גמרא's Gemara framing it
as like a hybrid as completely, you know, bizarre and can't be
categorized as anything.
Perhaps the תחש tahash is actually a billy goat, right? Yeah, perhaps
they picked it because it's such a mythological animal.
Oh, that's interesting. Like a centaur also.
This is when it comes out of a human mother? Yes. And
comes out of an animal?
We've left that behind. We're not dealing with that anymore.
Can I just ask a question? In this learned in ישיבות yeshivas
where the rabbis are never wrong?
Well, I would say that this is rarely learned in ישיבות yeshivas
because it is not a classic מסכת, masechet, it is not an
interesting, you know, interesting in the sense of interesting to bring up
like the types of normal challenging conceptual issues that classically ישיבות yeshivas
like to discuss.
But when דפים dapim like this are encountered in a ישיבה, yeshiva,
it's a good question. I really think it depends. Meaning, I'm sure
there's some ישיבות yeshivot that it's like אסור assur to even think,
raise the questions. There are others that raise the questions and dismiss
them. I don't know. You know what I mean? It's a range.
I can't give you an answer to that.
You know more than me.
Okay. Anyway, so we can go ahead and we can do a
little survey. All right. Anyway, so it says like this. Everybody agrees
that if it's a hybrid, even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would agree
it doesn't count. לא נחלקו, Lo nachloku, they are only debating והוא
שפניו אדם ונברא בעין אחת כבהמה. ve'hishah panev adam venivra be'ayin achat
kebehema. That it looks human, so normally we would go by the
face and that would be enough to give it a human status.
But one eye looks like a בהמה, behema, it's not 100% human
face. What? And one eye looks human. But one eye is different.
Is that enough to affect the human status of this? שרבי מאיר
אומר מצורת אדם, She'Rabbi Meir omer mitzurat adam, as long as it
has some of the human appearance of a human, it's enough. We
know in general רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir more ready to consider things
fetuses. So as long as it has a little, some of the
human and even if it's not some, 95% in terms of the
face, that's enough. וחכמים אומרים כל צורת אדם. Vachachamim omrim kol tzurat
adam. No, it has to be,
we're going to focus on the face and that has to be
completely look human or it does not have that status. אתו לקמיה
דרבי ירמיה בר אבא. Atu le'Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba. So they said
to רבי ירמיה בר אבא. Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba. האי איפכא תניא,
Hai ipcha tanya, we taught a ברייתא braita that actually
the positions are reversed. רבי Rabbi
and it's you know and more radically different from רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir than we've heard before. רבי מאיר אומר כל צורת, Rabbi Meir
omer kol tzurat, it has to be the entire appearance. Now again,
this is a radical shift, but we mean רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
would say if it all looks like a בהמה, behema, I'll consider
it to be a fetus, a human fetus. But if it's half
and half, then only if the entire face looks human. וחכמים אומרים
מצורת, Vachachamim omrim mitzurat,
it's enough that part of the face looks human. אמר להו, Amar
lehu, so he said back to them, אי תניא תניא, i tanya,
tanya, look if you got a ברייתא, braita, you got a ברייתא.
braita. That wasn't my tradition, but if you have a ברייתא, braita,
you know fine, that's your tradition. אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. So now
we're going to be more specific. רבי ירמיה בר אבא Rabbi Yirmeya
bar Abba says in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, מצח,
metzach, the forehead is quite again quite fascinating in terms of what
the rabbis thought were the parts of the face that most characterized
human. The forehead והגבינים ve'hagabinim the eyebrows והעיניים ve'haeinayim the eyes והליסטות
ve'halistot the cheeks וגבות הזקן, ve'gabbot hazakan, the chin, גבות הזקן, gabbot
hazakan, excuse me, והחן, ve'hachen, עד שכולם כאחד. ad she'kulam ke'echad.
They all have to be human in order for this fetus to
have a status of human. This is going to be a process
that has to have completely human features, at least in the face.
רבא אמר חסא, Rava amar Chasah,
רבא Rava says in the name of חסא, Chasah, interesting name of
a sage, means like lettuce. Anyway, here's no, it doesn't need everything,
מצח, metzach, the forehead, but not all of the other features, הגבן
hagaban one eyebrow's enough, עין ayin one eye, לסת leset one cheek,
וגבת הזקן vegabbat hazakan
and one sort of half of the chin. עד שכולם כאחד. Ad
she'kulam ke'echad. They all have to be there but it only has
to be basically half of the half of the features of the
face, not all of the double, you know, not all of the
twin parts of the face. So it says, and the גמרא Gemara
says, לא פליגי, lo peligi, they're really not debating you know, I
mean they are, but they're not debating in terms of principle. הא
כמאן דאמר כל צורת, Ha keman de'amar kol tzurat, הא כמאן דאמר
מצורת. ha keman de'amar mitzurat. There's the different opinions we said before.
If you said all of the appearance of a human, it has
to be all of these features and both halves of those parallel
parts. If you say some, as long as you have half of
the features, not all of again, of each, you need to have
all of the things, eyes, chin, etc., but you don't have to
have both halves. So enough to have one half of them that
suffices. Interestingly, it did not mention nose or ears. Ears in particular
is seen to be sort of less significant, which is interesting because
I think do other animals have this thing? Other animals' ears don't
look like this do they? Do they have the ear lobes? I
don't think so. There is, I think the ears are pretty distinctive
as human ears. But it's interesting that it's not mentioned. And again,
that has to be with, you know, the fact about looking at
somebody and the face, you know,
and that's so much how we identify personality and humanness is in
the face.
Their ears kind of come vertically to the head, right, rather than
on the side.
Right,
so there is something very distinctive about the human ears and nevertheless
the גמרא Gemara isn't addressing it because it's not just what's distinctive,
the body is also distinctive, it's about the humanness that we attach
to the face.
So what does it tell a mother then who gives birth to
a fetus that looks more like an animal?
Well, it's an interesting point, meaning I know what we were saying
yesterday or you were saying about that it's that we're not concerned
about what emotionally is going on and how we even sort of
suggesting like this isn't human so you're not so something's inhuman about
you is that like some implicit message? But in theory and maybe
I'm just trying to put a nice spin on it, it could
also be an issue
about like if a mother miscarries and the doctor says the child
really was never viable so it maybe makes it easier to deal
with the miscarriage right than if there was a viable child that
actually and was could have been brought to full term and there's
still a miscarriage? So sort of maybe by a little bit discounting
the importance of the fetus could make it also easier to deal
with it but I'm not saying that that's what's motivating the גמרא.
Gemara. The גמרא Gemara isn't asking what do we tell the mother
right other than are you טמא tamei or not טמא? tamei? That's
what the גמרא Gemara is asking.
What if it's live birth?
No, the גמרא Gemara all of this as we said yesterday.
I am just getting there.
No, all of that was and that was the גמרא's Gemara response.
Right. The גמרא's Gemara response was how is it a relevant right
how's it a relevant question none of these things are ever born
alive? That was the גמרא's Gemara answer at the end of yesterday.
But what if they are?
The גמרא Gemara assumes that that can't be at all that these
things are non-viable.
So if they are viable that would change the status.
Right, right. So that was and the גמרא Gemara just dismissed certain
questions because it says it's not viable anyway. Okay, let's finish this
up these animal features and then we'll go on to slightly different
one well whatever we're gonna keep on circling back. Anyway, so it
says like this מיתיבי Meitivei I object to this, צורת פנים שאמרו
Tzurát Paním She'ámru when they say the appearance of the face that
that's significant in the status, אפילו פרצוף אחד Afilu Partzuf Echad you
don't even need half of the features, even like one פרצוף Partzuf
now פרצוף Partzuf normally means the face but here פרצוף Partzuf means
one of the facial features one of the facial sort of components
אחד מן הפרצופים Echad Min HaPartzufim חוץ מן האוזן Chutz Min Ha'Ozen
again explicitly
sort of rejecting the ear but presumably this would at least include
nose. Anyway, למימרא דמחד נמי סגי Leimra DiMechád Namí Sagí so you
see you said all of the features or half this says even
one of them. אמר אביי כי תניא ההיא לעכב תניא Amar Abaye
Ki Tanyá Hahí Le'akév Tanyá
that's saying no when it's saying one it means if you're missing
one then it can't be human. Not one is enough but if
you're missing even one it's a problem. וכמאן דאמר כל צורה U'CheMan
De'Amar Kol Tzura like the opinion that you need all of the
features. איבעית אימא Iba'it Eima and if you want I could say
לעולם כמאן דאמר מצורה Le'olám KeMan De'Amar MiTzura one of the features
suffices, ומאי אחד אחד אחד U'Maí Echad Echad Echád and
what does it mean one? It doesn't mean just one it means
one no not every one but one of each pair as long
as you have one of each pair not just one.
אמר רבא Amar Rava okay fine now Rava says, ניברא בעין אחת
ובירך אחת מן הצד אמו טמאה Nivra Be'ayin Achát UveYarech Achát Min
HaTzad Imo Tme'ah now if a man or person whatever a fetus
is born with one eye and with one side right no two
eyes and it's not that he looks like an animal but he's
missing some of some of what makes some of the normal physical
qualities some of the normal appearances. So he doesn't have he only
has like half of his body not meaning not exactly half but
he only has one thigh he only has one eye. Okay, so
if it's מן הצד Min HaTzad if it's where it should be
on the body but he's missing the other one then אמו טמאה
היא Imo Tme'ah Hi the mother is טמאה tme'ah meaning maybe he'll
it's not viable maybe he's even born stillbirth or miscarriage but nevertheless
in terms of the appearance as long as they're on in the
right place even if it's only one of them that the mother
is still טמאה. tme'ah. We don't say it's not a considered a
fetus. It's a fetus just not viable. באמצע Be'emtza how about though
however if it's like a Cyclops? He's got the eye smack in
the middle or he's got or he's got the thigh coming out
from the center not from the one thigh sort of like a
tree trunk coming out from the center.
באמצע אמו טהורה Be'emtza Imo Tehorah then again even though that's not
like an animal that's not enough of a human appearance that the
mother would be considered to be טמאה tme'ah that it would be
a fetus.
Even if the rest of the face looks the same?
Everything else looks the same. So again what you see here is
again not the גמרא Gemara just saying oh this is an animal.
The גמרא's Gemara basically saying again for a fetus to make the
mother טמאה tme'ah it does not have to live obviously even a
miscarriage but it has to be sufficiently formed in terms of forty
days in terms of development and it has to be have enough
of a human appearance. So until now we've been doing an animal
appearance but here we're saying even if the human appearance is very
different than a normal human not that it's lacking but it's completely
different in where things are then that also was not enough of
a human appearance.
Part of the normal human body is
a malformation.
So yeah so that's like yeah that would be like a really
disturbing idea if the גמרא Gemara would say that even a live
birth if it was enough to form but I don't think we
see that.
I mean let's as we continue to
read see putting aside this whole animal issue. I mean, that's again,
I mean, I understand that it's been sort of a difficult דף
daf in many ways. It's even more difficult if you wonder whether
the גמרא Gemara is describing certain types of, you know, actual genetic
defects that could make these things look like this, and
maybe even in as you say, impossible live births. But we have
not found that. You know, the גמרא Gemara until now has all
been assuming that all of these things are non-live births. But so
I don't know. Let's keep on seeing what types of things the
גמרא Gemara describes this way. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara gets
moves a little bit away from appearances and goes to the question
about about viability. So let's take a look. אמר רבה, Amar Rava,
ושתא נקיב, weshta nakuv,
if the esophagus has a hole in it, אמו טמאה. imo tme'ah.
Okay, the mother is still טמאה. tme'ah. ושתא אטום, weshta atum, however,
if the esophagus was
basically sealed, you know, there really wasn't a tube there, it was
completely sealed, then אמו טהורה. imo tehorah. The mother is טהורה. tehorah.
Now, what is the I don't know, let's dissect.
Now,
what is I'm not kidding. Now, what is the difference? Okay, either
way, the child is born dead, it's a miscarriage. The difference is
as I is that if the child was never, you know, if
the development was not was not sort of leading to a possible
viable child, then the mother is טהורה. tehorah. If the child was
developing normally and then they just miscarried, then the mother would be
טמאה. tme'ah. So until now what we said normal type of development
versus non-normal was focused on the appearance. Here we're talking about normal
versus non-normal in terms of was this a type of development that,
had it gone to completion, the child could have been viable or
alive? So if it had a hole in the esophagus, we're assuming
that maybe could have been viable. But if the esophagus was completely
sealed, you know, there was no tube there, essentially it was all
like whatever, solid skin, then it was not a development that was
even in the process of leading to a viable to a viable
child and therefore the mother is not טמאה. tme'ah. You look like
you need to say something.
No, that's why it seems to be talking about a child born
alive, and the only way they would know is if they can
eat or can nurse.
How would they know? Were they going to cut it up?
That's what Michael asked. Yeah, so I don't know, I mean, can't
you sort of tap on some it's exposed, can't you tap on
something to see if it's hollow or not?
Well, there's another way to look at this. I mean, you know,
these are all like really strange cases, but in a way this
is how the גמרא Gemara
investigates questions about like what is human, what does it mean to
be human? So, you know, in a way, although it's kind of
icky for us,
but this may be a way of kind of working that out.
I mean, we would we would talk in more philosophical terms, we
do sometimes too, but maybe this is...
Right, and that's sort of what I said the other day about
the emphasis on the face is profound because, you know, like I
said, the whole people that discuss like, you know, that brain dead,
the the the that even brain death, the person should still be
considered alive because it can still do all these bodily functions and
they can gestate a fetus. They wouldn't say that if you had
the body there without the head. Oh, it can still do all
these bodily functions, so it's still alive. There's something very much about
humanness that we attach to the face and to the head. So
I definitely think that there's points about how the גמרא Gemara here
is thinking about the issue of of human identity. You don't agree?
No, but I
think that the idea
I mean, they could not have anticipated test tube babies or genetic
cloning or anything like that. So they had to it would have
been
the most logical to assume that humanness is a function of
how
you are born or the gestation or who your mother is, and
to have questions about whether you're human when the mother is clearly
human
just...
I know, but but I want to be careful. The גמרא Gemara
never said the גמרא Gemara is asking a very narrow question. It
is not saying is this human? It's saying is this considered a
ולד velad for the הלכה halacha of the mother being טמאה? tme'ah?
So, for example, the same way it says that if the child
was born with a sealed esophagus, you know, it's not the mother's
not טמאה. tme'ah. It never said that that makes it not human.
One of the qualities is is it is it is a viable
fetus developing? Or if it expelled before 40 days. Not saying it's
not human. It's just saying it has not reached a stage yet
of development. So I mean maybe you could say that means it's
not human, but anyway, this the גמרא Gemara is never framed this
as a question of is it human. I think we move there
because the initial discussion was about if it looks like an animal.
So before 40 days... Yes. A miscarriage does not make a woman
טמאה. tme'ah. Correct. Okay. And so we're only discussing after 40 days.
Correct. Right. So after 40 days she could be טמאה tme'ah unless
the child was
evidence of malformation.
Exactly. Even correct. Significant malformation. or developing in a way that it
won't be viable. Meaning malformation in terms of more physical external appearances,
which is what we've been discussing, or the internal organs are developing
in a way that they clearly wouldn't have been viable. תוספות Tosefot
says, yeah, yeah. So that is the sort of focus of the
גמרא. Gemara. We want to make it broad.
And that's why these twins, they'd say one head and four limbs,
and that they'd be they might think it was part animal because
they might have animal appearance.
That's interesting. I also want to point out by the way, if
it's not developing in a viable way and the גמרא Gemara said
that all these things that have animal appearances are not viable, then
you wonder why we need to have the discussion about animal appearances.
Just say because it's not viable. So I don't know exactly the
answer. Let's keep on going in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
Because if they were viable, they'd be they'd be able...
I don't know. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: המפלת גוף אטום Hamapelet guf
atum if somebody miscarries a Now, אטום atum until now has meant
sealed, but here we are going to see it means like like
it means actually lacking, like more like it's just the it's just
the, you know, trunk, right? It doesn't have all the all the
features or something. Yeah, yeah, yeah. We'll see. Not fully אטום. atum.
Anyway, missing certain missing certain limbs, אינה טמאה לידה. einah teme'ah leidah.
The mother is not because again that child would never was never
would never have been viable. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: המפלת. Hamapelet. Now
we're going to explain, I'm sorry, skip a line. ואיזהו גוף אטום?
Ve'eizehu guf atum? What's a גוף אטום? guf atum? רבי אומר: Rabbi
omer: כדי שינטל מן החי וימות. kedei sheyinnatel min hachai vayammut.
Enough is missing that had the child been alive without this sort
of thing, without this leg or whatever, you know, he would have
died. So basically it means it wouldn't have been viable. Okay, because
with this thing that lacking a person can't live. וכמה ינטל מן
החי וימות? Vekamma yinnatel min hachai vayammut? Okay, so how much is
that? That what how much of a lacking limb will kill a
person? רב זכאי אומר, Rav Zakkai omer, top of כ״ד ע״ב. kaf-dalet
amud-bet. רב זכאי Rav Zakkai said עד הארקובה, ad ha'arkuvah, until the
basically like Is
that from Ben Zakkai's father?
That could be, interesting. Until the knee. Now, this is an animal,
so there's like two knees of an animal. If I remember correctly,
this is the higher knee. רבי ינאי אומר: Rabbi Yannai omer: עד
לנקבה, ad lanekevah, until the actual until the genitalia, which means the
whole thigh of the leg is missing, not just the lower part
of the leg, the whole thigh. רבי יוחנן אומר Rabbi Yochanan omer
משום רבי יוסי
בן יהושע: mishum Rabbi Yosei ben Yehoshua: עד מקום טיבורו. ad mekom
tiburo. Not just the thigh to the genital area, but even like
above the waist, going all the way, you know, including all the
way until the navel.
Did you have any thalidomide babies like that? Okay.
Now, the גמרא Gemara says like this. So בין רבי זכאי לרבי
ינאי איכא בינייהו. Bein Rabbi Zakkai le-Rabbi Yannai ika beinaigu. What's the
debate of whether it's just the lower leg or the upper leg?
What's the what you know what's behind that the debate? טרפה חיה,
Tereifah chayah, whether we whether we assume that an animal once it's
a טרפה, tereifah, could it still live? Is it still viable? Because
the lower leg missing makes it already a טרפה. tereifah. So if
it's already a טרפה, tereifah, is that enough to say it's a
non-viable fetus? So מר סבר Mar savar טרפה חיה. tereifah chayah. One
says even if it's a טרפה tereifah it could be viable. So
the lower leg is not enough to make a difference. It has
to be missing the thigh as well. ומר סבר Umar savar טרפה
אינה חיה. tereifah einah chayah. The other one says no, once it
has the quality once it's missing a limb that makes it a
טרפה tereifah toward an animal, we're doing the anyway the comparison the
other way, then it's not viable. So lower leg because it's a
טרפה tereifah it's also not viable. So there they're just debating what
they're really debating is a medical question. I mean, it starts with
a הלכה halachic question, but in the end it's asking if it's
missing the lower leg is it viable or not. One says it's
it's not viable. How do I know? I know because it's a
טרפה. tereifah. On the other side, the fact that it's טרפה tereifah
doesn't prove anything. It's still viable unless it's missing the thigh as
well. One minute. בין רבי ינאי לרבי יוחנן איכא בינייהו. Bein Rabbi
Yannai le-Rabbi Yochanan ika beinaigu. Now how's that the debate about the
thigh versus does it have to be missing up to the navel?
איכא בינייהו Ika beinaigu דרבי אליעזר, de-Rabbi Eliezer, the debate of רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דאמר רבי אליעזר: De'amar Rabbi Eliezer: ניטל ירך וחלל
שלה. nittal yarech vechallal shelah. If the thigh and its hollow, like
you know, the whole sort of, you know, the whole sort of
like what do you call that, anyway the whole sort of socket,
yeah I think it means like the hip bone or whatever, anyway
if all of that is missing, נבלה. nevelah. It's considered already like
dead, not just a טרפה. tereifah. It's like it's already so much
is missing it's like you took the heart out. It's already dead
even before it's died. Now, the question is do we say that
or not. Meaning even if you say that missing the lower leg
isn't a טרפה, tereifah, here's a statement that okay but once it's
missing the thigh, not only a טרפה, tereifah, it's like you've already
killed it, right? So if you ripped out its heart you would
say it's already dead even before it's dead, so
if you tear off from the upper thigh it's already dead. So
that says okay so once the fetus is missing that much obviously
it's non-viable. The other disagrees, no, I actually think that things can
live without that and not until it's missing until the actual actual
navel. But again, here the debate is we've put totally aside appearance
issues and here the debate is a miscarriage makes the mother טמאה
לידה teme'ah leidah if the fetus was developing in a way that
it would have been viable. But if it's missing certain parts that
it would never have been viable, whether internal or external organs, then
it's not considered to make the mother טמאה. teme'ah.
In a separate issue, like let's say it has like some sort
of completely malformed with like three fingers and stuff like that.
Oh yeah, yeah, the גמרא Gemara never right Look, the גמרא Gemara
said even if it has only one arm. Right. So in terms
of appearances, all the גמרא Gemara has said and it's so funny
as I said why you need to have the discussion. category since
the גמרא Gemara also said that those other appearances are not viable,
but in terms of appearances what the גמרא Gemara has given us
is certain animal-like appearances and the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and the חכמים, Chachamim, or in terms of when it's not an
animal but just a type of deformed human, it's given this very
extreme case about an eye in the center or a trunk for
the body. Okay, but some other types of deformations are not in
the גמרא, Gemara, and that that's important because so far all these
descriptions I don't think are things that we ever encounter.
So you mean if it's missing the arm it would be a
problem, but if it has an arm and it's completely malformed
and it's not a problem, is that what you're saying?
Even if it's missing an arm it's not a problem. We're talking
about missing a leg. Okay, missing an arm is not... right, leg
is not the same thing. Correct, correct. Here it's not about appearances,
it's about viability.
A missing leg not viable.
Well, in animals, the גמרא Gemara thought it wasn't viable, and the
question the גמרא Gemara is assuming is that you can apply, you
know, you can apply from animals here. Why did the גמרא Gemara
even think that by animals that it's not viable? Yeah, I don't
know, it's a good question. Good question, why is it
actually by animals?
What? Even if it was a reality by animals.
Right, the גמרא Gemara does assume, generally assumes, that the טריפה treifa
categories by animals should be applied to humans although sometimes that's questioned.
Right, we're dealing with a missing leg?
Yeah, that's... you're right, never saw an animal with a broken leg
or with a missing leg. It's a good question. Maybe if you
don't have good medical science you die not from the missing leg
but from the infection and from the fact that, you know, and
so on and do they have a good way, I don't know,
you know, in the ancient times did they have a good way,
when soldiers lost legs in battle, were they able to keep them
enough that they could survive?
If you get fully formed without a leg there's no wound, it's
just missing. It's not bleeding from somewhere.
Right. Right. Are people born missing legs? It's happened
before. Yeah, alright, I don't know, I don't know. Very good question.
Let's keep on looking. The גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay, so
אמר רב פפא מחלוקת מלמטה למעלה, Amar Rappa machloket milmata lemala,
here again we get to the importance of the head. All of
these debates of how much is it missing? Is it things are
missing from the bottom up? How far from the bottom up does
it have to be missing to say that it's not viable? אבל
מלמעלה למטה, Aval milmala lemata,
if it's missing something from the top, from the
head, אפילו כל שהוא טהורה, afilu kol shehu tehora, even a little
bit is טהור. tahor. Now what does that mean? I mean, you
know, you could be a... you could have like a deformed skull
or a missing piece of the skull and imagine that the child
could still be viable. It's not missing, it's...
again, the question is:
is it deformed or is it missing? Right, so what's
missing? If we're not talking about the whole head isn't there, so
some part of the head isn't there. Okay, anyway, וכן אמר רב
גידל אמר רב יוחנן המפלת שגולגולתו אטומה, vechen amar Rav Giddel amar
Rav Yochanan hamappelet shegulgolto atuma, if somebody gives birth to a child
whose skull is like fused or, you know, whatever, it's like sealed,
not somehow it's like missing or not differentiated, אמו טהורה, imo tehora,
the mother is טהורה. tehora. But it doesn't tell you what that
means. Right, does it mean that, I don't know, does it mean
that like you don't have any facial features? We're actually going to
get to that later and that uses a different descriptor. Or does
it mean that, you know, there isn't a nose the same way
we talk about a body missing a leg or an arm? It's
again not really clear what the גמרא Gemara is getting at. Is
that the same as the eye? No, no, that was when it
looked like a different animal. Okay, so anyway, רש"י Rashi just says
שנחתך מגולגולתו shenichtach migulgolto a piece is missing, is cut away, and
אטומה atuma means חסרה, chaserah, some part is lacking. But again, it's
very... maybe the point is you don't have to be descriptive, that
any part is lacking, but, you know, that's... I mean, at least
for us, that's not so clear that it's not viable. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues: ואמר רב גידל אמר רב יוחנן המפלת
כמין אפקתא דדיקלא, ve'amar Rav Giddel amar Rav Yochanan hamappelet k'min afakta
d'dikla, if somebody gives birth to like a, a...
like a certain type of, of palm tree, which is, you know,
you've got, you've got like this trunk in the middle and at
the top you've got, you've got like, you know, these all of
these branches coming out of the top, right? So basically what happens
if you've got a human, the way רש"י Rashi describes it, that
basically has a trunk on the bottom and the legs and the
arms are cutting out, are coming out from the top? Okay, I
don't know if that's... again, if the גמרא Gemara is just imagining
this. But anyway, so what would be the story there?
אמו טהורה. imo tehora. I'm sorry, did I skip a line? אמו
טהורה. imo tehora. Yep, so again, it's טהורה. tehora. Why? Apparently not
because it doesn't... one imagines that here we're no longer dealing with
appearances, but the assumptions of viability, that seems to be our focus.
איתמר, Itmar, we talk. Now we're going back to the face. המפלת
מי
שפניו מושמסין, Hamappelet mi shepanav musmasim, if somebody that... the fetus has...
the face is, um, like smushed. That's a technical term. So you
basically have features, but they're all a little like, you know, smushed
down. רב יוחנן אמר אמו טמאה. Rav Yochanan amar imo tme'ah. The
mother is still טמאה. tme'ah. That again is still human enough in
terms of the features and it's viable, in theory. ריש לקיש אמר
אמו טהורה. Resh Lakish amar imo tehora.
No, the mother is טהורה. tehora. אותיביה רב יוחנן לריש לקיש. Eitevei
Rav Yochanan l'Resh Lakish. רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan asked ריש לקיש: Resh
Lakish: המפלת יד חתוכה
ורגל חתוכה, hamappelet yad chatucha v'regel chatucha, if a woman miscarries and
something comes out like a cut off arm, a cut off leg
from the fetus, אמו טמאה
ללידה. imo tme'ah leda. And you don't see the rest of the
fetus, so do... you assume that the rest of the fetus was
viable. Okay, because if you can't see it, but maybe say well
maybe not, it's got these things falling off, maybe it was one
of these weird cases and not a problem. So the משנה mishnah
says no, you have to assume that it's a problem. ואין חוששין
שמא מגוף אטום
בא. ve'ein chosheshin shema m'guf atum ba. You don't have to- you
don't have to be concerned that maybe the body was, you know,
was somehow misformed and not developed and so on. Maybe it was
developed fine but now in the process of the miscarriage these things
broke off. But you don't have to be concerned about a complete,
you know- about a misformed- that the mother is טהורה. tehorah. So
now he says, well what is that relevant to the case of
the face? So he says, ואי איתא, ve'i isa, if you're right
that there's a case of a smushed face that also is- the
mother is טהורה, tehorah, נתני שמא מגוף אטום או ממי שפניו מסמסים.
nisni shema m'guf atum o mimi shepanav musmasin.
Why
does it not say we don't have to be concerned whether the
body was misformed or whether the face was misformed? Okay, because meaning
he's basically like- you could say why don't you say a million
things? But the point is is that if it's saying
what types of things could make the mother טהורה, tehorah, so why
is it just describing the body? If you're right that there's types
of things like the face- again, we're not talking about looking like
animals, right, we're talking about deformed in the sense of not de-
you know- not viable or not having certain human features, but whatever,
why only describe we're not concerned that there were problems in the
body? Why not say we're not concerned that there were problems in
the face? Clearly even if the face is smushed, it is not
a problem. Now of course it's a question-both-challenge because everybody agreed before
that certain problems in the face, right, would be a problem, right,
if it had only one eye in the center or if it
had animal features or whatever. But anyway, that's his argument. If that's
true that there are face problems, it should have been mentioned here.
So now let's take a look at how the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר רב פפי, Amar Rav Pappi, so said Rav Pappi, where are
we, מסמסים כולי עלמא לא פליגי דטמאה. musmasin kuli alma lo pligi
detmei'ah.
You know what? You're right. When it's smushed facial features- they're human
but they're smushed- everybody agrees that the mother is טמאה. tmei'ah. It's
considered human appearance, it's viable and so on. כי פליגי בפניו טחות.
ki pligi bepanav tuchot.
We're not talking about the smushed, we're talking about completely flattened, like
basically almost like, you know, sort of like eradicated facial features. Not
that there wasn't a nose and there wasn't eyes or whatever, but
somehow something happened that completely somehow flattened them and much more than
just smushed them
down. דאיכא דאמרי, de'ika d'amri, and they were taking the other side
of the debate. רבי יוחנן אמר אמו טהורה Rabbi Yochanan amar immo
tehorah that in that case the mother is טהורה. tehorah. Again, why?
Is it because of the assumption that it is- it is not
viable? Here we seem to be echoing back the previous part and
again the importance of the face. So whereas before we were talking
about facial features not looking like animals, here we're talking about human
facial features but completely sort of- completely like, you know, what's the
word I'm looking for?
Anyway, completely
effaced, you know, so they were human features but they no longer-
they've been completely flattened and therefore is that enough to have a
human appearance? It seems here again that the issue is appearance and
not viability. So- so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says the mother is
טהורה. tehorah. וריש לקיש אמר- ve'Reish Lakish amar effaced! That's the word
I was looking for. I'm serious, the entire facial features have been
effaced, you know, the face of them has been removed. רבי יוחנן-
Rabbi Yochanan okay- וריש לקיש אמר- אמו טמאה. ve'Reish Lakish amar immo
tmei'ah, Yeah, that's a good point. Well the סנדל sandal is the
entire fetus, right? Not just the face. That's the entire fetus. This
is just the face, but it's a similar point. Okay, but here
the emphasis on the face. רבי יוחנן- Rabbi Yochanan okay so anyway-
רבי יוחנן אמר אמו טהורה Rabbi Yochanan amar immo tehorah ורבי שמעון
בן לקיש אמר אמו טמאה. ve'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish amar immo tmei'ah.
That's a good point. Yeah, I don't know, it does sound like
a סנדל, sandal, you're right. וריש לקיש אמר ve'Reish Lakish amar אמו
טמאה, immo tmei'ah. that no even in that case the mother is
טמאה. tmei'ah. וליחשב ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן מהא. velichshav Reish Lakish leRabbi
Yochanan me'ha. So why didn't Reish Lakish challenge Rabbi Yochanan from this
case about, oh we're not concerned that the body was problematic? Why
didn't it also say we're not concerned that the face was completely
effaced, the face of the features? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
משום דשיני ליה, mishum deshini leh, because he would just answer, היינו
גוף אטום. hainu guf atum.
It's the same way it says we're not concerned that the body
was lacking, that's essentially considered part of it.
The face completely lacking the features is like the body lacking the
features. The question before was when we said even if the features
are there, if they're deformed and smushed, if that was true it
should have been mentioned. But if the only time we're going to
say טהורה tehorah according to Rabbi Yochanan is when the facial features
are completely wiped away, then that's basically the same as when we
said parts of the body are missing. So here's a body part
that's missing, the body part are those types of facial characteristics. So
what have we said now? We've said- we had the whole animal
discussion. Then we shifted into something that had nothing to do with
facial features and emphasis on the face but facial features that look
like animals. Then we had a shift that had nothing to do
with appearances had all to do with viability. That obviously miscarriage yes,
but only if the fetus was developing in a way of viability.
Questions about esophagus, leg, things that would make it considered not viable.
Now we've moved back to the question about appearance and again with
an emphasis on the face but not because it has an animal
look. But because somehow even those human features have somehow been deformed
and effaced and how much does that affect the status. So let's
now see the next point. Is it the debate at the end
about the face totally flattened when it's effaced? Yes, so in the
end the גמרא Gemara is saying that that's the debate of רבי
יוחנן ריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan Resh Lakish and the reason it's not
relevant from the case that says if missing parts of the body
is because completely effaced is a missing part of the body and
it's therefore not a different category. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: בני רבי חייא, Bnei Rabbi Chiya, the sons of
רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, נפיק לקרייתא, nafik l'kiryata, they went out to
the city. אתו לקמיה, atu l'kamei, then they came to him, דאבוהון,
d'avuhon, in front of their father after their little field trip. אמר
להם, amar lahem, he said to them, כלום מעשה בא לידכם, klum
ma'aseh ba liyadechem, did you have any interesting things happen to you
when you were on your trip? And it's not just interesting things,
מעשה ma'aseh means halakhic issues. Did you have any halakhic issues that
you encountered? So אמרו לו, amru lo, פנים טוחות באו לידינו. panim
tuchot ba'u liyadeinu. Yes, somebody asked us about a case about a
fetus that was born and the face was completely, the facial features
were completely wiped away, effaced. וטימאנוה, v'timanuha, and you should be very
proud of us because we were very strict and that even though
before, you know, it said that there was a debate of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and normally we would go
like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan or whatever, we said that the mother
was טמאה, teme'ah, even though the face was completely, the facial features
were wiped away. ואמר להם, v'amar lahem, he said to them, צאו
וטהרו מה שטימאתם, tze'u v'taheru mah shetimatem, go back and tell the
mother that she is טהורה. tehorah. מה דעתייכו, mah da'ataychu, what were
you thinking? לחומרא, l'chumra, to be strict? חומרא דאתי לידי קולא היא.
chumra d'ati liyadei kula hee. This is a חומרא chumra that leads
to a קולא. kula. Why? Because when you say the mother was
considered a childbirth, then the mother has טומאת לידה, tum'at leidah, so
once you're giving her טומאת לידה, tum'at leidah, דהויא לה ימי טוהר,
d'havya lah yemei tohar, not only is she going to make herself
טמאה teme'ah for a week or two weeks, but then the next
thirty-three or sixty-four days she's going to assume that any blood is
blood that follows a childbirth and she's טהורה. tehorah. So you cannot
play it safe and be מחמיר machmir and therefore you have to
give the real פסק, psak, and the real פסק psak in this
case is that she is טהורה tehorah when the face facial features
were wiped away and were effaced. Now of course this is a
very important principle, you know, about the whole approach to חומרא, chumra,
is that how, you know, you think you can always be מחמיר,
machmir, very often חומרות chumrot lead to קולות kulot either obvious ones
or unintended ones, and that's obviously a larger discussion. Okay, איתמר, itmar,
המפלת בריה, hamapelet biryah, now someone gave birth to a creature, you
know, a, you know, to some type of a fetus שיש לה
שני גבים ושתי שדראות. sheyesh lah shenei gabim ushtei shidra'ot. So there
you go, רבקה, Rivka, it sounds like that could be what's describing.
It effectively has two backs and two spinal cords. It doesn't say
it has two heads, and you wonder where the head is if
it's got the, I mean if it had two heads would you
think it would have said it? So it has one head and
where do the backs come in? And the גמרא Gemara talks about
the two heads. I know, I'm not exactly seeing how the גמרא,
Gemara, anyway. Spines from one neck, just like branches off I guess.
Okay, anyway. Could be one body with two spines but just not
fully separated. Oh, it can? They don't fully separate? It could be
one skull and two... I thought that means it's two separate things
that are at the point where they joined at some point. Like
conjoined twins. In animals it's somewhat... Alright, a third but an angle.
Right, right. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר רב, amar Rav,
באשה אינו ולד. be'ishah eino valad. If this is a fetus, it's
not considered halakhically a fetus and the mother is not טמאה. teme'ah.
Apparently, right. So this is considered somehow enough and again here he's
saying not because it looks like an animal, not because it doesn't
have human features, but somehow it has, it's a little bit like
the case about the eye in the center of the head. It
is so completely deformed that we would not consider it to have
enough of the appearance of a human. And obviously again when you
think about as this raised questions about real birth defects and, you
know, deformations, it's again is the גמרא Gemara describing humanity but it
is describing a human appearance, you know. So, so המפלת בריה, hamapelet
biryah, so anyway, באשה אינו ולד, be'ishah eino valad, by a woman
it's not considered to be a fetus. בבהמה אסורה באכילה. bevehemah asurah
ba'achilah. If an animal gave birth to a something like this, it
would not be considered like we had before the discussion of an
animal giving birth or having in its womb something that looked human,
so this also takes it out of the normal animal category. Wait,
what about the שסועה? shasu'ah? That one? Okay, take a, we'll take
a look. So anyway, so therefore it would be forbidden. That's, that's
what רב Rav said. ושמואל אומר, u'Shmuel omer, באשה ולד. be'ishah valad.
No, by a woman it is considered a fetus and she's טמאה.
teme'ah. ובבהמה מותרת באכילה. uvevehemah muteret ba'achilah. And by an animal it's
permissible. Okay, so במאי קמיפלגי? bemai kamiflegi? What do they debate? בדרבי
חנין בר אבא. bid'Rabbi Chanin bar Abba. דאמר רבי חנין בר אבא.
de'amar Rabbi Chanin bar Abba. So here, Mike, remember, although Mike you
remember it in the reverse, השסועה. hashasu'ah. So the תורה Torah says
this is what you cannot eat. Here רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק,
pasuk, it is את זה לא תאכלו, et zeh lo tochelu, this
is what you shall not eat. It says something, something והשסועה, ve'hashasu'ah,
with the split hoofs. So according to this רבי חנין בר אבא,
Rabbi Chanin bar Abba, he says השסועה hashasu'ah is a description of
a strange type of an animal that is forbidden. that's forbidden. So
and this is an animal that has these two backs and two
spines. So that's his, and he believes that there's like a new
creature of an animal that is like this. So how does it
relate this position? Let's take a look. ויש שיש לו ב׳ גבין
וב׳ שדראות. ve-yesh she-yesh lo bet gavin u-bet shidra'ot. רב אמר, Rav
amar, so רב Rav who says that it's not a ולד. vlad.
בריה בעלמא ליתא, biryah be-alma leita, that actually such a type of
a creature does not normally exist. Meaning it was it's never viable,
it doesn't exist, it never you never have an animal that's walking
around and you
never have a fetus that's viable, and therefore for the mother she's
not טמאה לידה,
tmeya leida, for the animal that if it's actually if it's actually
so okay, so בריה בעלמא ליתא, biryah be-alma leita, it does not
exist as an independent animal. וכי אגמריה רחמנא למשה, ve-chi agmreih rachmana
le-moshe, when did God have to tell משה Moshe that treat this
as a non-kosher animal? במעי אמה אגמריה, be-mei imma agmreih, when it's
in the mother's womb. Okay, the only place such a thing will
exist is in the mother's womb. It will never be born viable.
And therefore for a human being it's not a ולד, vlad, and
for animals it won't be it's not born viable, so it's a
moot question. And if it's in the mother's womb, we have this
דרשה drasha that tells you it's forbidden. So that's רב's Rav position.
It's forbidden, it's not viable, end of story. Now how about שמואל?
Shmuel? שמואל אמר בריה בעלמא איתא. Shmuel amar biryah be-alma ita. Yes,
actually such a thing can be viable. So so okay, and therefore
if it's and therefore if it's in the mother's womb, it's a
ולד vlad because it is viable. So here you have a case
of a significant deformity, which according to שמואל Shmuel because it is
viable,
it is considered a ולד. vlad. Okay, and according to רב Rav
the only issue
seems to be that it was not viable. So therefore it is
viable, for the mother it's a ולד. vlad. So how about this
fact that it's supposed to be forbidden? So וכי אגמריה רחמנא למשה,
ve-chi agmreih rachmana le-moshe, so when God taught משה Moshe that there's
this animal called a שסועה shisu'ah that's forbidden, בעלמא אגמריה, be-alma agmreih,
that's only when it's walking around and it's an independent thing. Or
רש״י Rashi might say it's a separate species of animal, not when
it's born by a normal cow mother. אבל במעי אמה, aval be-mei
imma, but it isn't walking around and certainly or you could add,
and when it clearly has a normal cow mother, then שריא, sharya,
it's permitted. Dealing with a normal mother, right? Or some yeah, if
you read it that way. So basically the point is, is what
they're arguing is is such a thing viable or not? And and
if you say it's viable, then even though it's significantly deformed, it
still is considered to be a ולד. vlad. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues, and whether such a thing right. איתיביה רב שימי
בר חייא לרב. eitiveih Rav Shimi bar Chiyya le-Rav. רב שימי בר
חייא Rav Shimi bar Chiyya asked רב. Rav. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס
אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonos omer, we have a משנה Mishna that
says רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonos says, כל שיש
לו ב׳ גבין וב׳ שדראות. kol she-yesh lo bet gavin u-bet shidra'ot.
Now here we're talking about a human, a כהן. kohen. If a
כהן kohen has two backs and two spines, again the fact that
it's always being discussed means that they must have obviously been deal
it seems to be dealing with a real case. Anyway, פסול לעבודה.
pasul la-avoda. Such a כהן kohen cannot do the עבודה. avoda. That's
a מום. mum. So now there's a problem though. What's not a
problem, but if you have to say that it's a מום mum
and he's פסול לעבודה, pasul la-avoda, you are assuming that he's viable.
Thank you very much. So אלמא חיי, alman chai, you see that
it's viable and רב Rav said it wasn't viable. So אמר ליה,
amar leih, so רב Rav said to him, שימיא, Shimyya, אח שימיא,
ach Shimyya, you are שימיא. Shimyya. רש״י Rashi has a whole discussion
why he says שימיא, Shimyya, but anyway, שימי Shimi was his grandson.
So רש״י Rashi just says it's a term of endearment. So oh
שימי, Shimi, my dear שימי, Shimi, ששדרתו עקומה. she-shidrato akuma. That is
talking about a case not literally two backs and two spines. That's
talking about a case of a bent spine. Not I don't know
if a hunchback. What's that case about? Know people have scoliosis? Yeah,
yeah, so that anyway, so he says that's a case of a
deformed spine. It's not talking about a double spine. Double spine although
it says double spine, but a real double spine and double back
is not viable, that is something that looks that way but isn't
actually that way. מיתיבי meitivei says the גמרא Gemara says, I'll ask
you on this. יש בעוברין שהן אסורין. yesh be-ovarin she-hein asurin. There
are cases of fetuses which are forbidden, in the case where meaning
if it is if it is a minute, yeah, which are born.
Meaning here's again a question of viability. Some type of animal fetuses
are born, but if they're not viable they're essentially like a נבילה
neveila or טרפה, treifa, and even if you שחט shacht them they're
not kosher. So you need an animal to be considered viable if
you want to שחט shacht it and eat it. So there are
some type of fetuses that are born, might be alive now but
are not viable and cannot be eaten. And how do you what's
the determination? And here we have really have a focus on degree
of development, okay? So יש בעוברין שהן אסורין, yesh be-ovarin she-hein asurin,
בין ד׳ לדקה, bein daled le-dakka, if it's born within four months
of a small animal, a sheep or goat, the normal gestation period
is five months. בין ח׳ לגסה, bein chet le-gassa, or eight months
for a cow where the normal gestation period is nine months. הימנו
למטה, heimennu le-mata, anything from that point and less of a development,
אסור assur is forbidden because the animal will cannot survive and therefore
is essentially like a טרפה. treifa. יצא מי שיש לו ב׳ גבין
וב׳ שדראות, yatza mi she-yesh lo bet gavin u-bet shidra'ot, but that
excludes the case of two backs and two spines. So wow, how
what does two backs and two spines have to do with fetal
development? So like how you know how many months? So let's see
how the גמרא Gemara understands what this is talking about. מאי יצא,
mai yatza, what does it mean? not be a problem but in
the womb they're okay as opposed to a case of two spines
which is forbidden even in the womb and that's how they want
to read that ברייתא braisa and that seems to support רב Rav
that two spines is a problem even in the womb. So let's
take a look. So רב מתרץ לטעמיה Rav metaretz le-taamei ושמואל מתרץ
לטעמיה. ve-Shmuel metaretz le-taamei. רב Rav explains according to his reasoning and
שמואל Shmuel explains according to his reasoning. So רב מתרץ לטעמיה, Rav
metaretz le-taamei, רב Rav explains according to his reasoning, בן ארבע לדקה
בן שמונה לגסה. ben arba le-daka ben shemona le-gasa. Now we're going
to re-say what we said before. Four months for a small, eight
months for a large animal, הימנו ולמטה אסור heimenu u-lemata asur is
forbidden. במה דברים אמורים, Bamei devarim amurim, when is that true? כשיצא
לאויר העולם, Keshe-yatza le-avir ha-olam, once it's born. אבל בימי אמו, Aval
bi-mei immo, a fetus in the mother's womb by an animal, שרי
shari is permissible when you shecht the mother. יצא מי שיש לו
שני גבים ושני שדראות, Yatza mi she-yesh lo shenei gavim u-shenei shidraot,
as opposed to a fetus that has these two backs and these
two spines, דאפילו בימי אמו אסור, de-afilu bi-mei immo asur, that even
in the mother's womb it's forbidden. Why? Because remember רב Rav said
that דרשה drasha of השסועה ha-shasua only applied as in the womb
because such an animal would never live anyway. So he says in
the womb this is forbidden. And that's how he reads it. So
it's a זה? ze? It sounds like it's a person. I know,
but anyway. So anyway, so therefore that's how he reads it, that
supports his read. How would שמואל Shmuel read this ברייתא? braisa? בימי
אמו נמי אסור Bi-mei immo nami asur is also forbidden. ושמואל מתרץ
לטעמיה ve-Shmuel metaretz le-taamei explains according to his reasoning. בן ארבע לדקה
בן שמונה לגסה, ben arba le-daka ben shemona le-gasa, for four and
eight months, הימנו ולמטה אסור, heimenu u-lemata asur, any less than that
when an animal is born is forbidden and it's not viable. במה
דברים אמורים שלא כלו לו חדשיו, Bamei devarim amurim she-lo kalu lo
chodashav, when is that true? When it is when the months are
not complete. Meaning when it does not have, you know, these are
a problem because they have not fully developed. אבל כלו לו חדשיו,
Aval kalu lo chodashav, if the months have fully developed, מותר mutar
it's permissible. יצא? Yatza? Meaning it's three months, three full months is
permissible? What are you saying? What is כלו? kalu? Meaning this is
a problem because it hasn't fully developed. But once it's fully developed,
it's fine. Actually, the גמרא Gemara also sometimes considers the possibility that
a thing even less than the full amount of months could be
fully developed at קוטטי. koteti. But the point is here the only
problem is lack of full development and once it's fully developed it's
not an issue. יצא, Yatza, this excludes the case of מי שיש
לו בי גבים ובי שדראות, mi she-yesh lo beis gavim u-veis shidraot,
an animal that has the two backs and the two spines, דאף
על פי דכלו לו חדשיו, de-af-al-pi de-kalu lo chodashav, even if it's
completely fully developed, אם יצא לאויר העולם אסור, im yatza le-avir ha-olam
asur, once it's born it's forbidden. Why? Because this is this case
of the השסועה. ha-shasua. Okay? בימי אמו שרי, Bi-mei immo shari, but
as a but the exact opposite of רב, Rav, in the mother's
womb it's still permissible, then it's considered to be part of the
mother. Okay, so that ends up this strange case of the two
backs and the two spines. But again what's interesting from that is
that we are dealing with something that we're saying is once we
assert that it's viable, even with this significant deformity, we are saying
that the mother is טמאה לידה, tameia leida, so here's an actual
case where the deformity is not considered to change its status if
we can assume that it's viable. Okay, so now we continue with
this and we say and we say like this. Where are we?
Ah, okay. תני תנא קמיה דרב, Tani tana kamei de-Rav, so a
תנא tana recited in front of רב, Rav, המפלת כמין גוף שאינו
חתוך, ha-mapeles ke-min guf she-eino chatuch, if somebody, if a woman miscarries
and basically like a trunk which is not have you know it's
not literally cut, meaning it's not divided into limbs. Okay fine. בראיית
ראש שאינו חתוך, be-riyas rosh she-eino chatuch, or a head that is
not you know that basically the features are not formed, it all
looks like a square, like a block. יכול תהא אמו טמאה לידה,
yachol tehei immo tameia leida, maybe the mother would be טמאה לידה,
tameia leida, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, אשה כי תזריע וילדה זכר, isha
ki tazria ve-yalda zachar, for a woman gives forth seed and gives
first birth to a male, וביום השמיני ימול, u-vayom ha-shemini yimol, on
the eighth day you shall circumcise. מי שראוי לברית שמונה, Mi she-rauy
li-vriyas shemona, something that is fit for basically for making it to
the eighth day. יצאו אלו שאינם ראויים לברית שמונה, Yatzu elu she-einam
reuyim li-vriyas shemona, as opposed to these, these could never in theory
have developed to a point that they could have had a ברית
מילה, bris milah, which is basically just a source of the פסוק
pasuk of the idea we've been saying until now, which is viability.
That although again a miscarriage is טמאה לידה, tameia leida, but the
child has to be on the path of developing towards a viable
child. If it's not on the path of developing towards a viable
child, then the mother is not טמאה לידה tameia leida and here
we're quoting it based on this verse. Okay. אמר ליה רב, Amar
lei Rav, so רב Rav said, ותני בה הכא, vesinei ba hacha,
that's a great ברייתא, braisa, add the following line at the end
of it. כששיש לו שני גבים ושני שדראות, ke-she-yesh lo shenei gavim
u-shenei shidraot, and also if it's got if it's got two you
know two spines and two whatever that's also... backs and two spines,
that's also excluded because that's also not in this category of viable.
Okay, but anyway, so this is again the assertion of not appearance
but viability, and it doesn't mean that the fetus has to be
born, but it has to mean it was on the path of
developing toward a viable child. Now, where were we? רבי ירמיה בר
אבא Rebbi Yermiya bar Abba סבר למעבד עובדא כוותיה דשמואל. savar lemavad
uvda kevasei deShmuel. If he wanted to rule like שמואל Shmuel in
a case, again, sounds like they really had these cases a lot,
about the two backs and the two spines. And he wanted to
say that a woman gave birth to this, and he wanted to
say against רב Rav that the mother was טמאה לידה. temeia leida.
So אמר ליה רב הונא, amar lei Rav Huna, so רב הונא
Rav Huna said to him, מאי דעתך? mai da'atach? לחומרא? lechumra? You
want to be strict and say the mother is טמאה לידה temeia
leida like שמואל Shmuel who says that it's viable? חומרא דאתי לידי
קולא. chumra de'asi lidei kula. That sounds familiar. It's a חומרא chumra
that leads to a leniency, because if you're going to treat the
mother as a יולדת, yoledes, you make her טמא, tamei, but then
you'll make her טהור tahor with bleeding afterwards. So don't try to
be strict. Just do the הלכה. halacha. So עביד מיהא כוותיה דרב,
avid miya kevasei deRav, you might as well rule like רב Rav
who says that it is not viable and the mother is not
a יולדת. yoledes. Why? דקיימא לן הלכתא כרב באיסורי, dekayma lan hilchasa
keRav be'issurei, because our rule is we go like רב Rav when
it's issues of איסור והיתר issur veheter as opposed to monetary civil
issues, בין לקולא בין לחומרא, bein lekula bein lechumra, whether lenient or
whether strict. So basically, don't fool around, don't try to be strict,
just פוסק, posken, and therefore we go like רב. Rav. Okay. אמר
רבא. Amar Rava. הרי אמרו, Harei amru, אישה יולדת לתשעה ויולדת לשבעה.
isha yoledes letisha viyoledes leshiva. Now normally we say, right, this is
the very interesting idea, although some people said that there was some
scientific basis for this, but anyway the גמרא Gemara understood that a
child born in the ninth month or the seventh month is viable,
but the eighth month is not viable. Very strange. But the גמרא
Gemara says we say that by humans. Would we say the same
thing by animals? We said an eight-month-old fetus is not viable; if
you slaughtered it, it's not כשר, kosher, it's like a נבלה neveila
or טריפה. treifa. What about if it's born in the seventh month?
Would we say the same thing we say by humans by animals?
Is it going to be above? No question. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, או לא. o lo. So we said אישה יולדת לתשעה
ויולדת לשבעה. isha yoledes letisha viyoledes leshiva. בהמה גסה, Behema gasa, יולדת
לתשעה. yoledes letisha. We know a large mammal like a cow is
normally nine months. יולדת לשבעה או לא? Yoledes leshiva o lo? Can
it be also give birth to a viable calf in the seventh
month? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, I'm
just going to the משנה. Mishna. Hopefully I'll do it in five
minutes if you have to leave, I understand. אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, תא שמע. ta shema. שמונה ולמטה
אסור. shemona ulemata asur. The ברייתא braisa said any eight month and
anything less, it's forbidden by a calf born to a cow. So
you see, anything less is not viable. We don't say the same
as we say in humans. So מאי לאו אגסה? mai lav agasa?
Is that not referring to the cow case? לא, אדקה. Lo, adaka.
No, it's referring to the sheep case. Four months or less is
forbidden, but by a cow, not everything less than eight months is
a problem. The גמרא Gemara says הייא מאי? hai mai? How can
you say that? אי אמרת בשלמא אגסה, Ei amart bishlama agasa, if
we're talking about the cow case, איצטריך. itztariach. You need to tell
me that less than eight months is a problem. סלקא דעתך אמינא,
Salka da'atach amina, I would have thought הואיל ובאישה חיי, ho'il uve'isha
chai, since we say by a woman a seven-month-old child can live,
בהמה נמי חיי, behema nami chai, I would have thought like you're
trying to argue, that it's true also by a בהמה, behema, that
seven months is better than eight months. קא משמע לן דלא חיי.
Ka mashma lan dela chai. So it tells me no, no, no,
animals eight months and less is not viable, as opposed to humans.
That makes sense why you would be saying that. אבל אי אמרת
אדקה איתמר, Aval ei amart adaka itmar, but if it's only talking
about the sheep case, פשיטא, pishita, of course that's true. בת תלתא
ירחי מי קחיי? Bas slasa yarchi mi kachai? Who would think that
a three-month gestated sheep could live? The גמרא Gemara says no, איצטריך,
itztariach, I still need to tell you. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'atach
amina, I would have thought כבציר תרי ירחי חיי. kebatzir srei yarchai
chai. Maybe we could sort of generalize the rule. Like humans, nine
and seven is okay. Cows, nine and seven is okay. Maybe sheep,
five and three works. Anything two months back can also be viable.
קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, no. But maybe it's only saying
by sheep three months is no good, but by cows maybe they're
like humans and seven months is still viable. So we don't have
an answer to that. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel, המפלת, hamapeles, and here we have one, we have to
end by a really good, another case of this appearances. And רבקה,
Rivka, this is something you mentioned yesterday, so get ready for this.
המפלת דמות לילית, Hamapeles demus Lilith, if the child looks like לילית,
Lilith, okay, which is like a human with wings, that's the way
רש"י Rashi describes it. I don't know how's לילית Lilith appear in
mythology? Winged, a winged, anyway. אמו טמאה לידה. imo temeia leida. So
that is enough of a human appearance because it just has, everything
is human except it also has wings. So the mother is טמאה
לידה. temeia leida. ולד הוא, Vlada hu, it's a fetus, אלא שיש
לו כנפיים. ela sheyesh lo knafayim. It's also got wings. That's not
enough to take it out of human appearance. תניא נמי הכי. Tania
nami hachi. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rebbi Yosi, מעשה בסימוני, ma'aseh biSimuni,
there was a case in סימוני, Simuni, באחת, be'achas, with a certain
city, and one woman שהפילה דמות לילית, shehipila demus Lilith, that the
fetus looked like לילית, Lilith, ובא מעשה לפני חכמים, uva ma'aseh lifnei
chachamim, it came to the sages, ואמרו ולד הוא, ve'amru vlada hu,
it's a fetus, אלא שיש לו כנפיים, ela sheyesh lo knafayim, it
has something extra, but it still has the status of a fetus.
Now, המפלת דמות נחש, hamapeles demus nachash, let's say the fetus looked
like a snake. Remember before we mentioned the snake and the question
that its eyes have a human appearance and we were discussing that?
So let's take a look. הורה חנניה בן אחי של רבי יהושע.
Hora Chananiah ben achi shel Rebbi Yehoshua. So חנניה, Chananiah, רבי יהושע's
Rebbi Yehoshua nephew, ruled אמו טמאה לידה. imo temeia leida. He's טמאה,
temeia, presumably because like we said before, maybe it has, the eyes
look human. הלך רבי יוסי Halach Rebbi Yosi Specific things before Rabban
Gamliel. Rabbi Yossi was a little bit shocked and he told Rabban
Gamliel, who was the נשיא, nasi, and he said, you gotta put
an end to this, he is giving these crazy פסקים. psakim. So
שלח לו, shalach lo, so Rabban Gamliel sent to Rabbi Yehoshua, to
Rabbi Yehoshua, who was the uncle, but were more of a position
of authority and there is all stories about Rabban Gamliel and Rabbi
Yehoshua you might remember about asserting authority. You can people who some
people know what I am talking about. Anyway, הנהג בין אחיך, hanhag
ben achecha, go grab your nephew ובא, u-va, and come to me.
I got some I got some business with you guys. So go
bring your nephew in front of me. He did not like the
ruling. ובאזילותן, v'azilotan, as they were going, יצתה כלת רבי חנינא לקראתו.
yatzas kalas Rabbi Chanina lipratey. So Rabbi Chanina's now actually, I am
sorry, יצתה כלת חנינא, yatzas kalas Chanina, yeah. Rabbi Chanina's daughter-in-law came
to him. אמרה לו, amra lo, and she said to him, רבי,
Rebbi, רבי, Rebbi, המפלת כמין נחש מהו? hamapelet k'min nachash mahu? What
is the story if maybe she was saying it happened to her.
What is the story if the childbirth looks like a snake? אמר
לה, amar lah, he says so Rabbi Chanina says to her, אמו
טהורה, immo tehora, it is not a problem. Now now you remember
before we had what did we have? We had Chananya ben achi
shel Rabbi Yehoshua said אמו טמאה. immo tme'ah. Here he is saying
טהורה. tehora. Maybe he understands that he is in big trouble. I
do not know why this was such an issue it had to
come to Rabban Gamliel, but but obviously he is getting in big
trouble, he is being shlepped in front of Rabban Gamliel. So now
he switched his position. Okay, טהורה. tehora. Fine, טהורה. tehora. So אמרה
לו, amra lo, she said to him, והלא שמך אמרת לי חמותי?
v'halo shimcha amart li chamoti? But my mother-in-law, who is his daughter-in-law's
mother-in-law? His wife. Did not your wife say to me in your
name remember we said if the rabbi was here he would tell
you so your wife told me in your name אמו טמאה, immo
tme'ah, that the mother is טמאה, tme'ah, which is why he is
in trouble because that's apparently what he's been ruling in this case,
that the mother is טמאה. tme'ah. ואמר לה מאיזה טעם? v'amar lah
me-eizeh ta'am? And she so he said to you what reason, you
know, did she give you for for saying that the mother that
it was טמאה? tme'ah? הואיל וגלגל עינו עגול כשל אדם. ho'il v'galgal
eino agol k'shel adam. So because because the eye looked like a
human eye. Okay, as we said before, and therefore טמאת לידה. tme'at
leida. So therefore they had this whole exchange. Basically Rabbi Chanina was
in trouble, being shlepped by his uncle Rabbi Yehoshua, had an exchange
with his daughter-in-law where he was trying to back out of his
position. His daughter-in-law insisted that it was his tradition his position, and
he said explicitly, you know what? You're right, and here was the
reason I said it because of the eye looks like a human
eye. So through that whole discussion, what happened? Rabbi Yehoshua is there
shlepping him and says to him, מתוך דבריה, mitoch devareha, out of
her what she said and the discussion, נזכר רבי יהושע. nizkar Rabbi
Yehoshua. Rabbi Yehoshua remembered, oh my gosh, that's right actually, the mother
should be טמאה, tme'ah, and that's a good point because the eye
looks like whatever and actually I you you I myself have ruled
that way, Rabbi Yehoshua remembered. So שלח לו לרבן גמליאל, shalach lo
l'Rabban Gamliel, so he sent to Rabban Gamliel, מפי הורה חנניה. mipi
horah Chananya. Actually, his ruling was based on a ruling that I
had given. I'd totally forgotten that I had paskened that way. This
whole discussion with the daughter-in-law reminded me about what my reason for
my פסק psak was and he should not be in trouble. Now
the question is: Is he in trouble because the ruling was wrong
or is he in trouble because, you know, the whole case with
Rabbi Yehoshua and Rabban Gamliel are often cases about like authority? Rabbinic
authority, you know, political authority, who is in charge. Maybe he was
in trouble not because it was a big deal what the פסק
psak was, but maybe he was in trouble because what is he
doing going around paskening on his own against the party line? Like
who gave him the authority to pasken? So now Rabbi Yehoshua said,
actually, it was on my authority. I had forgotten that I had
given this פסק, psak, but he should not be in trouble because
he was actually, you know, he was actually paskening on my authority.
אמר אביי שמע מינה amar Abbaye shma mina from here we see,
צורבא מרבנן דאמר מילתא, tzurba me-rabanan d'amar milta, that if a a
Torah scholar says something, לימא בטעמיה. leima b'ta'ameh. He should not just
give the פסק, psak, he should give the reason. Why? דכי מדכרו
ליה מדכר. d'chi madkru lei midkar. Because then you can remind him
of the reason and he will remember what he paskened. If you
just say, you said מותר, mutar, you said אסור, asur, he says,
I can't why would I have said such a thing? No, don't
you remember? You told me because of this and because of that.
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, that is right. Yeah, yeah, it is okay.
So so you should give the reason because that will help you
remember what you had actually said, which was the case here.